Sergei Kovalev Collection 1974-1990 Mss.Ms.Coll.35
American Philosophical Society
Sergei Kovalev Collection
1974-1990
Mss.Ms.Coll.35
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Linear feet
The electrophysiologist Sergei Adamovich Kovalev (1932- ) was a prominent Russian dissident and human rights activist. After earning an international reputation for his research on the electrophysiology of myocardial tissues, Kovalev became involved with Andrei Sakharov and others in founding the Initiative Group for the Defense of Human Rights in the USSR, and he was a major figure in the distribution of The Chronicle of Current Events, a samizdat news letter that became the primary uncensored source for information about the dissident movement. He was arrested by the Soviet authorities in December 1974 and sentenced to seven years in prison and three more in exile. After the fall of the Soviet Union, Kovalev entered politics and won election to the Russian Duma. The Kovalev Collection consists of files of correspondence, circular letters, and miscellaneous published materials pertaining to the Soviet dissident scientist, Andrei Kovalev. The collection is arranged in two Series of approximately equal size, representing the activities of two of Kovalev's supporters: Paul F. Cranefield of Rockefeller University, who helped mobilize support for Kovalev in the United States, and Silvio Weidmann a physiologist at the University of Bern, who operated in Europe. Both Cranefield and Wiedmann were in regular contact with one another and both worked with professional organizations, with human rights groups such as Amnesty International, and with fellow activists such as Rosa Last.
Kovalev, Sergei Adamovich, 1932-
Related Archival Materials note
The APS houses a small number of collections with material on Soviet science, all from an earlier period and mostly centered on Lysenkoism. The papers of Theodosius Dobzhansky (B D65), L. C. Dunn (B D917), I. Michael Lerner (B L563), Conway Zirkle (B Z67), Ernst Caspari (Ms. Coll. 1), and Milislav Demerec (B D394) all have material on Lysenko in Russia. The papers of Dunn, Bronson Price (Ms. Coll. 16), Raymond Pearl (B P312), and Franz Boas (B B61) include material on scientific exchange with Russia in the 1930s, and Curt Stern (Ms. Coll. 5) in the 1960s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Paul F. Cranefield, June 1990 (accn. no. 1994-78ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Kovalev Collection consists of files of correspondence, circular letters, and miscellaneous published materials pertaining to the Soviet dissident scientist, Andrei Kovalev. The collection is arranged in two Series of approximately equal size, representing the activities of two of Kovalev's supporters: Paul F. Cranefield of Rockefeller University, who helped mobilize support for Kovalev in the United States, and Silvio Weidmann a physiologist at the University of Bern, who operated in Europe. Both Cranefield and Wiedmann were in regular contact with one another and both worked with professional organizations, with human rights groups such as Amnesty International, and with fellow activists such as Rosa Last.
Because Cranefield and Weidmann worked closely together on the Kovalev case, the two Series both complement one another and provide a measure of duplication. Both series include correspondence to and from Cranefield and Weidmann attempting to rouse support for Kovalev, circular letters from other activists and human rights organizations regarding the case and regarding the conditions of Kovalev's health, and the well being of his family, and numerous clippings from newspapers, professional journals, and the mass media providing a gauge of public and professional opinion.
Biographical/Historical note
In 1969 Kovalev was working as a senior fellow in biology at his alma mater, Moscow University, when he was released due to his political activities. Already known as a dissident, he joined Andrei Sakharov and others in 1969 in founding the Initiative Group for the Defense of Human Rights in the USSR. Despite his dismissal, Kovalev managed to continue his scientific career, working at an experimental fish hatchery on problems in chemical mutagenesis, and he persevered as an activist. In 1974, however, the Soviet authorities once again intervened and his scientific career ended. In 1973, Kovalev and two colleagues, Tatiana Velikanova and Tatiana Khodorovich, resumed publication of The Chronicle of Current Events, a samizdat news letter that became the primary uncensored source for information about the dissident movement. Produced secretly using typewriters and carbon paper (since the Soviet authorities restricted use of photocopiers), the Chronicle defended the gamut of repressed and dissident groups, and was correspondingly perceived as a significant threat to the government. One year later, Kovalev also became a founding member of the USSR branch of Amnesty International, while his increasing visibility as a supporter of other dissidents added further fuel to the fire.
On December 23, 1974, the KGB raided Kovalev's apartment in Moscow, confiscated his files on prisoners of conscience, and sent him to a prison in Vilius, Lithuania, to await trial. Charged formally with anti-Soviet agitation and propaganda carried on for subverting or weakening the Soviet regime, Kovalev faced a laundry list of specific allegations: association with The Chronicle of the Lithuanian Catholic Church, the longest running dissident journal in the Soviet Union, being a member of the Initiative Group, signing appeals on the first anniversary of the invasion of Czechoslovakia, supporting other dissidents and political prisoners, sending information on the Soviet gulag abroad, and resuming publication of The Chronicle of Current Events. Sakharov responded by denouncing the charges as little more than a pretext to clamp down on dissidents of all sorts.
Kovalev pleaded not guilty, and in an "open" trial filled with irregularities, he was sentenced to seven years in a labor camp and three years of exile. Fresh off his Nobel Prize, Sakharov led protests against the conviction in Russia, while colleagues, concerned scientists, and other human rights activists outside of Russia began a campaign to petition Soviet authorities for his release. Although these efforts kept Kovalev's case in the public eye, they did little to shorten Kovalev's term, and after his release in 1984, he was barred, as the court had directed, from living in Moscow, making a living at menial jobs.
Kovalev was finally allowed to return to Moscow in 1987 and resumed his activities on behalf of human rights. After the fall of the Soviet Union, he entered politics, winning election to parliament beginning in 1990. Even in office, he remained consistent in his stance on human rights, protesting against human rights violations in Chechnya, arguing that "the most influential forces in Russia today are attempting to establish an authoritarian regime."
Adler, Judith; Amnesty International; Boitsova, Lusya; Cranefield, Paul F. (Paul Frederic), 1925-; Eisner, Thomas, 1929-; Gallone, Selene; Hesburgh, Theodore Martin, 1917-; Kovalev, Ivan; Last, Rosa; Sakharov, Andrei, 1921-1989; Weidmann, Silvio; Human rights--Soviet Union; Photographs; Political prisoners--Soviet Union
- Series I. Paul F. Cranefield material, 1976-1990; 0.5 lin. feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Cranefield's files are a diverse assemblage of correspondence, circular letters, newspaper and magazine clippings, and other miscellaneous materials pertaining to Paul Cranefield's activities on behalf of Sergei Kovalev and, to a lesser degree, other prisoners of conscience. In addition to documenting Cranefield's numerous letters to professional journals, colleagues, public officials, and the media, the series includes extracts of letters from Kovalev's wife, Lusya Boitsova, and from other concerned Russians that appear to have circulated widely among supporters of the dissidents, and numerous circular letters conveying news of Kovalev's precarious health in prison. The clippings from newspapers and journals provides a gauge of public and professional response to Kovalev's imprisonment.
  One of the best documented parts of the Cranefield series is the 1979 effort to arrange a boycott of the Comparative Electrocardiology meeting held at Syktyvkar and the XX International Symposium on Electrocardiology held at Yalta. Responses to the call for boycott by Cranefield and Weidmann were predominantly positive, however some colleagues felt that such action would only worsen Kovalev's case, while others felt that politics should not intervene.
  The Cranefield files are arranged chronologically by year.
  - Chronological file, 1976; 12 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1977; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1978; 29 items (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with Rosa Last, Petitions, etc.
  - Chronological file, 1979; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1980; 8 items (Box 1)
    Includes updated biography of Kovalev.
  - Chronological file, 1981; 34 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1982; 10 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1983; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1984; 12 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1987; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1989; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Chronological file, 1990; 2 items (Box 1)
- Series II. Silvio Weidmann material, 1974-1990; 0.5 lin. feet
  Silvio Wedimann's files includes valuable documentation of the European response to Kovalev's arrest and imprisonment, and contain the same scope and range of materials as Series I.
  The Weidmann files are arranged topically, in essentially chronological order. The collection begins with some biographical material on Kovalev and photographs, followed by material on Kovalev's arrest, a series of petititons from European cardiac electrophysiologists, files on Kovalev's imprisonment, and groups of correspondence with Rosa Last and Amnesty International. The arrangement reflects the order of the collection as received from the donor.
  - Photographs, bibliography, biography, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes "A survey of the scientific activity of S. A. Kovalev."
  - Material on Kovalev's arrest, 1974-1975; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes, inter alia, letters from Yuri Yakobson and Je. Rivkin to Weidmann, 1974, from Yuri Golfond to the New York Times, Mar. 27, 1975, and petition of electrocardiologists to V. Kotelnikov, Pres. Of the Academy of Sciences of the USSR, July 15, 1975.
  - Replies to Weidmann, 1975-1979; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2a)
    Includes 47 letters from fellow scientists, mostly offering support for Kovalev.
  - Petitions to Anatolii Alexandrov, President of the Akademia Nauk SSR, and Leonid Brezhnev, 1978 Dec. 19-21; 1 folder; European cardiac electrophysiologists (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Petitions denouncing the arrest of Kovalev.
  - Petition to Anatolii Alexandrov, 1979 Nov. 20; 1 folder; European cardiac electrophysiologists (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Petition denouncing the imprisonment of Kovalev.
  - Petition to Sergei Kovalev, 1980 Oct. 17; 1 folder; European cardiac electrophysiologists (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Petition to Leonid Brezhnev, 1981 Oct. 12; 1 folder; European cardiac electrophysiologists (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Petition to Prokuratura at Moscow and Magadan, 1982 Sept. 27; 1 folder; European Cardiology Society (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Petition to Prokuratura at Moscow and Magadan, 1983 Dec. 10; 1 folder; European Cardiology Society (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Petition to Prokuratura at Moscow and Magadan, 1984 Sept. 18; 1 folder; European Cardiology Society (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Updates on Kovalev, 1976-1980; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes extracts from letter of Elena Sakharov, July 1976, and from co-detainee Wolf Zalmanson, June 3, 1979.
  - Christophol Prison, 1980-1982; 13 items (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Internal exile, 1980-1982; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Material concerning Kovalev's release, 1983-1989; 8 items (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kovalev, Ivan, 1978-1988; 11 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Soviet boycott, 1976-1980; 54 items (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes invitation from M. Roshchevsky to attend the National Symposium on Comparative Electrocardiology after the International Symposium in Yalta, 1979; clippings from newspapers and magazines on Russian political prisoners.
  - Soviet boycott, colleagues' responses, 1979; 45 items (Box 2, Folder 15a)
  - Last, Rosa, 1979-1986; 26 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - United States institutions, 1975-1986; 34 items (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Amnesty International, 1976-1990; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18a)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1981; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)